Charles Baldwin Sedgwick Papers
Charles Baldwin Sedgwick Papers
1814-1891
Sedgwick, C. B. (Charles Baldwin), 1815-1883.
1.75 linear ft.
Papers of the New York State lawyer, U.S. Congressman (1859-1863), abolitionist, born near Pompey, N.Y. Correspondence (1847-1891); genealogical material; legal and financial records (1814-1879); writings (1837-1884), including essays, speeches, and published letters; and memorabilia. Largely family correspondence with additional letters of Louis Agassiz, Samuel Bowles, Salmon P. Chase, F.J. Child, James Freeman Clarke, Roscoe Conkling, George W. Curtis, John A. Dahlgren, Richard H. Dana, H.L. Dawes, Daniel S. Dickinson, J.T. Fields, John M. Forbes, John C. Frémont, William Lloyd Garrison, George W. Geddes, George F. Hoar, John Jay, Thomas Starr King, Samuel J. May, Robert B. Minturn, Levi P. Morton, Charles Eliot Norton, Elizabeth P. Peabody, Wendell Phillips, William H. Seward, Gerrit Smith, Israel Washburn, R.S. Watson, Andrew D. White, and others.
149575
Biographical History
Charles Baldwin Sedgwick (1815-1883) was an American attorney and U.S. Congressman from New York State. While an attorney in Syracuse he was a member of the defense counsel for the Jerry Rescue case.
Sedgwick was born on March 15, 1815 near Pompey, New York. His parents, Stephen and Anne Baldwin Sedgwick, sent him to Pompey Hill Academy. Later in 1834 he graduated from Hamilton College. Around 1835 he married Ellen Smith who died in 1846. In 1847 Sedgwick married Deborah Gannett of Cambridge, Massachusetts.
In 1846 Sedgwick moved from Pompey to Syracuse, N.Y. and opened a law office. During the latter part of the decade he became involved with various social reform causes, particularly the anti-slavery movement. He was affiliated with American Anti-Slavery Society, and was a member of the Syracuse Vigilance Committee which aided runaway slaves. Sedgwick was one of the attorneys for the defense in the Jerry Rescue Case.
Sedgwick was elected to Congress in 1859 where he served two consecutive terms as the representative of the twenty-forth District. As a member of Congress he distinguished himself as an anti-slavery advocate, and as Chairman of the Navy Committee. In 1863 he returned to private life, and the practice of law.
See the attached genealogical table for the Sedgwick family tree.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Charles B. Sedgwick Papers consist of correspondence, legal and financial Records, memorabilia, and writings.
Correspondence, 1847-1891, consists largely of letters written by Charles Baldwin Sedgwick to various members of his family, especially his wife. These discuss family matters as well as subjects with broader social implications. Some of the letters concern his duties in Congress and the progress of the Civil War. About one third of the correspondence consists of letters written to Sedgwick by his family and various associates. Among this latter group are a number of notable individuals including Roscoe Conkling, John A. Dahlgren, William Lloyd Garrison, John Jay, Wendell Phillips, and Gerrit Smith. An index to selected correspondents appears at the end of this finding aid.
Legal and financial records, 1814-1879, consist of routine documents pertinent to the business affairs of the Sedgwick family. It also contains a few items that pre-date Sedgwick's birth.
Memorabilia dating from 1862 to 1883 contains various items of incidental interest including clippings, biographical material, and obituaries of Charles B. Sedgwick and his son Frank.
Writings date from 1837 to 1884. There are essays, published letters, and speeches authored by Charles B. Sedgwick. Of special interest in this section is an essay, probably written by Sedgwick, on "The Legal Conditions of Women," 1837. There is also a small group of writings by others.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is in chronological order. The remaining series are in alphabetical order by type or title.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Politics, government and public administration; Activism and social reform; Civil War (U.S.); Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873.; Bowles, Samuel, 1826-1878.; Chase, Salmon P. (Salmon Portland), 1808-1873.; Child, Francis James, 1825-1896.; Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888.; Conkling, Roscoe, 1829-1888.; Curtis, George William, 1824-1892.; Dahlgren, John Adolphus Bernard, 1809-1870.; Dana, Richard Henry, Jr., 1815-1882.; Dawes, Henry L. (Henry Laurens), 1816-1903.; Dickinson, Daniel S. (Daniel Stevens), 1800-1866.; Fields, James Thomas, 1817-1881.; Forbes, John Murray, 1813-1898.; Frémont, John Charles, 1813-1890.; Garrison, William Lloyd, 1805-1879.; Geddes, George W. (George Washington), 1824-1892.; Hoar, George Frisbie, 1826-1904.; Jay, John, 1817-1894.; King, Thomas Starr, 1824-1864.; May, Samuel J. (Samuel Joseph), 1797-1871.; Minturn, Robert Bowne, 1805-1866.; Morton, Levi P. (Levi Parsons), 1824-1920.; Norton, Charles Eliot, 1827-1908.; Peabody, Elizabeth Palmer, 1804-1894.; Phillips, Wendell, 1811-1884.; Sedgwick, C. B. (Charles Baldwin), 1815-1883.; Sedgwick family.; Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872.; Smith, Gerrit, 1797-1874.; Washburn, Israel, 1813-1883.; Watson, Robert Spence, 1837-1911.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.; Abolitionists -- United States.; Lawyers -- New York (State); Slavery -- United States -- Anti-slavery movements.; Social reformers -- United States.; New York (State) -- History.; Syracuse (N.Y.), History.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Essays.; Genealogies (histories); Speeches (documents); Abolitionists.; Lawyers.; Social reformers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Fragments (Box 1)
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - [General], Mar 1847-Nov 1860; 24 folders (Box 1)
  - [General], Dec 1860-May 1864; 22 folders (Box 2)
  - [General], Jun 1864-Feb 1891; 26 folders (Box 3)
- Legal and financial records
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3)
  - Bills and receipts, 1867-1879; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Certificate of Appointment, Master Examiner, 1841 (Box 3)
  - Rockefeller property, 1814 (Box 3)
  - Specifications for house construction, undated (Box 3)
- Memorabilia
  - Fragments (Box 4)
  - Biographical material (Box 4)
  - Clippings (Box 4)
  - Obituaries, 1862-1883 (Box 4)
- Writings
  - Essays
    - "The Legal Condition of Women #2", 1837; holograph (Box 4)
  - Published letters
    - On anti-slavery, 1851 (Box 4)
    - On Abraham Lincoln, eulogy, 1865 (Box 4)
  - Speeches
    - Acceptance of donation on behalf of the board of trustees of Wells College (Box 4)
    - "Emancipation and Enrollment of Slaves In the Service of the United States", 1863 (Box 4)
    - On old Pompey Academy, undated (Box 4)
    - "An Oration Before Sigma Phi", 1850; printed material (Box 4)
    - "To Raise Additional Troops", 1863; printed material (Box 4)
    - "The Republican Party: The Result of Southern Aggression", 1860; printed material (Box 4)
    - "State of the Union", 1861; printed material (Box 4)
  - Miscellany
    - "A Girl of Sixteen at Brook Farm," by Deborah G. Sedgwick, manuscript of essay published in the Atlantic Monthly, March 1900 (Box 4)
    - "Wendell Phillips," pamphlet by George William Curtis, 1884 (Box 4)
    - Verse, printed material (Box 4)
Selected index to correspondence
All items are to Charles Baldwin Sedgwick, unless otherwise noted.
[ ], Raymond 1860 Mar 24
Agassiz, Louis 1864 Mar 17
Andrews, [ ] 1860 Apr 19
Barten & Guestier 1877 Aug 16
Bowles, Samuel 1875 Apr 8
Calvin, D.C. 1853 Jun 10
Chase, Salmon P. 1861 Jul 30
Child, F.J. 1861 May 19
Clarke, James Freeman 1860 Apr 16
Conkling, Roscoe ca. 1855 Nov 9 1860 Jul 12 1860 Jul 19 1863 Mar 26 1869 Mar 8
Curtis, Anna Shaw 1872 Aug 20 (to Deborah G. Sedgwick)
Curtis, George W. 1860 Jun 17 1861 Jun 28 1861 Jul 9 1861 Aug 20 1861 Sep 1 1861 Sep 6 (to Deborah G. Sedgwick) 1862 Jan 27 (to Deborah G. Sedgwick) 1862 May 20 1863 Nov 22 1869 Oct 7 1869 Oct 23 1870 Jul 16 (to Deborah G. Sedgwick) 1871 Sep 11 (to Deborah G. Sedgwick) 1871 Sep 14 (to Deborah G. Sedgwick) 1871 Oct 27 1878 Feb 8 1891 Feb 9 (to Deborah G. Sedgwick)
Dahlgren, John A. ca. 1861 Jul 10 1865 Aug 21 (to Deborah G. Sedgwick)
Dana, Richard H., Jr. 1862 Dec 4 1865 Apr 25 (to Deborah G. Sedgwick)
Dawes, H.L. 1869 Mar 1 1883 Feb 9 (to Deborah G. Sedgwick)
Dickinson, D.S. 1861 Feb 23
Ellis, Meamy K. undated
Field, John W. 1862 Jan 2 1863 May 1
Fields, J.T. undated
Forbes, John M. 1861 Jul 17 (telegram) 1861 Jul 17 1862 Mar 18 1862 Jun 7 1862 Jul 2 1862 Jul 13 1864 Jun 3
Forbes, John W. ? Jul 27 1879 May 25 1862 Aug 4 1863 Jul 10
Fremont, John C. 1861 Dec 17
Garrison, William Lloyd 1862 May 20 1851 May 10 (to Deborah G. Sedgwick)
Geddes, George 1860 Mar 20 1860 Apr 20
Gott, Anne undated
[Grimms?], J.W. 1862 Jul 31
Hoar, George F. 1884 Nov 28 (to CBS?)
Howell, [John H.?] 1863 Jan 1
Jay, John 1862 Apr 20 1862 Jul 7
Kennedy, G.H. 1861 Jul 8
King, Thomas Starr 1861 Oct 24
Lathrop, J.H. 1853 May 22
May, Samuel J. 1860 Apr 4 1862 Jun 5 (to ?)
Minturn, Robert B. 1863 Mar 25 1863 Jun 12
Morton, Levi P. 1864 May 3
Norton, Charles Elliot ca. 1861
Norton, Grace 1854 Jan 22 ca. 1861 (on reverse, Charles Elliot Norton to CBS) ca. 1860 Dec 30
Peabody, Elizabeth P. 1860 Apr 19
Phillips, Wendall 1860 Apr 15
Porter, Daniel D. 1863 Dec 6
Quintard, George W. & Edward P. Rozus 1863 Jul 22
Rogers, T.[?] S. 1877 Apr 11
Sedgwick, C.M. undated 1859 Jun 27 1856 Jul 28 (to ?)
Sedgwick, Charles 1847 Mar 15 1847 May 19 1847 Jun 7 1847 Jul 21 1849 Mar 28 1849 May 18 1849 Jun 22 1850 Apr 7 1851 Feb 16 1851 Apr 30 1851 Dec 18 1852 Jul 18 [1853?] Jan 19 1853 Mar 3 1853 Mar 8 1853 Jun 9 1853 Jun 16 1853 Jul 10 1853 Jul 10 1853 Sep 2 1854 Nov 22 1854 Nov 31 1855 Jul 20 1863 Dec 14 (to Deborah G. Sedgwick)
Sedgwick, Charles Hamilton 1862 Dec 31 (to Deborah G. Sedgwick)
Sedgwick, E.R. 1860 Apr 22
Sedgwick, John 1863 Jan 23 1864 Jun 27
[Sedgwick?], Melly 1847 May 12
Sedgwick, S.J. 1884 Mar 10 (to Deborah G. Sedgwick)
Seward, William H. undated
Smith, Gerrit 1860 May 14 1860 Nov 15 1870 Jul 4 1872 Dec 27 (to Deborah G. Sedgwick)
Smith, Gordon 1864 Oct 5
Valerio, J. 1860 May 11
Washburn, Israel, Jr. 1861 Jan 22 (CBS?) 1862 Jun 2 1862 Sep 11
Watson, R.S. 1863 Jul 10
White, Andrew D. 1876 Oct 5
Wilkinson, [Alfred?] 1860 Apr 22 1861 Jul 4 1861 Jul 8 1861 Jul 12
Wise, [Henry Augustus?] 1863 Apr 20 1863 Jun 30
Wister(?), Sarah B. 1865 Apr 28 (to Deborah G. Sedgwick)